<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>app.unisic.Unisic</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name>Unisic</name>
  <developer id="app.unisic">
    <name>Unisic maintainers</name>
  </developer>
  <summary>Capture, annotate, record and share your screen on Linux Wayland</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Most screenshot tools hand you a rectangle of pixels and walk away. Unisic
      covers the whole workflow that starts the moment you press the hotkey:
      annotate directly on the selection overlay before the shot is even taken,
      keep editing afterwards, record the same region as a GIF or video, and push
      the result wherever it belongs — clipboard, disk, or a custom upload
      destination with the link ready to paste.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Capture full screen (multi-monitor), an interactive region, or a specific window</li>
      <li>Annotate on the overlay before the capture is finalized — ShareX-style</li>
      <li>Post-capture editor: arrows, shapes, freehand, text, blur/pixelate, crop, numbered steps, highlight, object cutout with background removal, undo/redo</li>
      <li>Record a region or the full screen to GIF, MP4 or WebM, with optional system and microphone audio</li>
      <li>Modular upload destinations (custom HTTP/FTP/SFTP/API), auto-copy the link, upload history</li>
      <li>Tray icon, configurable global hotkeys, and optional OCR to copy text out of a capture</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Built for Wayland on legitimate APIs only (xdg-desktop-portal, KWin
      ScreenShot2, PipeWire, KGlobalAccel). KDE Plasma gets the fully silent
      native capture path; other desktops work through portals. Zero telemetry.
    </p>
  </description>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">app.unisic.Unisic.desktop</launchable>
  <categories>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>
  <url type="homepage">https://unisic.app</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/unisic/unisic/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/unisic/unisic</url>
  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#C8ACD6</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#17153B</color>
  </branding>
  <screenshots>
    <!-- TODO: replace with real UI screenshots (overlay, editor, recorder)
         before the Flathub review round — this is the project banner. -->
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/social-preview.png</image>
      <caption>Capture, annotate, record and share your screen</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <provides>
    <binary>unisic</binary>
  </provides>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.2.2" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.2.1" date="2026-07-09" />
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-07-07" />
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-07-07" />
  </releases>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
</component>
