<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>app.unisic.Unisic</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name>Unisic</name>
  <developer id="app.unisic">
    <name>Unisic maintainers</name>
  </developer>
  <summary>Capture, annotate, record, share</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Most screenshot tools hand you a rectangle of pixels and walk away. Unisic
      covers the whole workflow that starts the moment you press the hotkey:
      annotate directly on the selection overlay before the shot is even taken,
      keep editing afterwards, record the same region as a GIF or video, and push
      the result wherever it belongs — clipboard, disk, or a custom upload
      destination with the link ready to paste.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Capture full screen (multi-monitor), an interactive region, or a specific window</li>
      <li>Annotate on the overlay before the capture is finalized — ShareX-style</li>
      <li>Post-capture editor: arrows, shapes, freehand, text, blur/pixelate, crop, numbered steps, highlight, object cutout with background removal, undo/redo</li>
      <li>Record a region or the full screen to GIF, MP4 or WebM, with optional system and microphone audio</li>
      <li>Modular upload destinations (custom HTTP/FTP/SFTP/API), auto-copy the link, upload history</li>
      <li>Tray icon, configurable global hotkeys, and optional OCR to copy text out of a capture</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Built for Wayland on legitimate APIs only (xdg-desktop-portal, KWin
      ScreenShot2, PipeWire, KGlobalAccel). KDE Plasma gets the fully silent
      native capture path; other desktops work through portals. Zero telemetry.
    </p>
  </description>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">app.unisic.Unisic.desktop</launchable>
  <categories>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>
  <url type="homepage">https://unisic.app</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/unisic/unisic/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/unisic/unisic</url>
  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#C8ACD6</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#17153B</color>
  </branding>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/screenshots/capture.png</image>
      <caption>Pick full screen, region or window and what happens after the shot</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/screenshots/editor.png</image>
      <caption>Annotate with arrows, numbered steps, blur and crop, then copy, save or upload</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/screenshots/record.png</image>
      <caption>Record the screen, a region or a window to MP4, WebM or GIF</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/screenshots/destinations.png</image>
      <caption>Modular upload destinations with the link copied after every upload</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/unisic/unisic/main/docs/screenshots/settings.png</image>
      <caption>Searchable settings with import and export</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <provides>
    <binary>unisic</binary>
  </provides>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.6.1" date="2026-07-12">
      <description>
        <p>Fixes global hotkeys on GNOME: shortcut registration now carries the app identity on a dedicated D-Bus connection, so binds no longer fail for terminal and AppImage launches. The version footer shows the exact git-commit date of the build, the hotkeys-unavailable card explains the GNOME custom-shortcuts route, and 42 missing translations were filled in.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.0" date="2026-07-12">
      <description>
        <p>Fully automatic updates: the app checks GitHub daily, AppImage installs download and swap themselves in place (restarting when idle), and deb/rpm downloads register the signed OBS/COPR repository on install so every later version arrives natively through the package manager. New Updates section in Settings.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.1" date="2026-07-11">
      <description>
        <p>Fixes region recording on multi-monitor setups. Adds a dedicated copy-last-capture shortcut (replacing the 2-second Ctrl+C grab), Ctrl+C on the selection overlay, capture-on-release, a separate recordings folder and a trash sound.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.0" date="2026-07-11">
      <description>
        <p>Editable shapes and shape groups in the editor, OCR text selection, richer text styling, Spanish and Italian translations, and a separate sound cue when a recording or GIF finishes encoding.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2026-07-10">
      <description>
        <p>New app ID app.unisic.Unisic (backed by unisic.app). Stale menu and autostart entries from older installs are cleaned up automatically.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.2.2" date="2026-07-10" />
    <release version="0.2.1" date="2026-07-09" />
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-07-07" />
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-07-07" />
  </releases>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
</component>
